erasmusplusols.eu 2017-08-15

# Privacy statement | Erasmus+ OLS

The following statement explains our policy regarding the processing of your personal data.

## Overview

The Erasmus+ Online Linguistic Support (hereinafter "OLS") is an initiative of the European Union. It is part of [Erasmus+](http://ec.europa.eu/programmes/erasmus-plus/index_en.htm), the EU programme for Education, Training, Youth and Sport. It is steered by the European Commission and implemented by its Education, Audiovisual and Culture Executive Agency (hereinafter "EACEA").

The OLS is dedicated to respecting the privacy of its users. It provides a secured and safe environment for mobility participants to learn foreign languages. The following statement outlines the policies by which the OLS collects, manages and uses the data provided by its users.  
As the OLS – which encompasses the licence management tool, the language assessment, as well as the language courses – collects and further processes personal data, it is subject to Regulation (EC) no 45/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December 2000 on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data by the European Community institutions and bodies and on the free movement of such data _ **[1]**_.

The various tools present on the OLS allow users to submit information in order to participate to OLS activities. When registering online and submitting other information, the data is collected and further processed for the purposes detailed hereafter under point 1. The relevant processing operations thereof are under the responsibility of the Data Controller, who is the Head of Unit A1 - Erasmus+: Schools, Prospective Initiatives, Programme Coordination at EACEA (see point 6 below for contact information).

## 1\. What personal information do we collect, and for what purpose?

### (a) Information relative to mobility participants:

The National Agencies, beneficiary institutions and the European Commission's DG EAC transmits some personal data to the EACEA, such as your e-mail address. The following information may then be collected directly from you by the EACEA through the OLS tool.

**Mandatory registrant data** : last name, first name, gender, contact e-mail, nationality, year of birth, mother tongue, type of mobility, language to test, country of destination, estimated start of the mobility, sending institution, mobility period, time zone, estimated end of the mobility.

**Results of language assessment and courses**

**Other optional data** submitted by mobility participants on the OLS (e.g., messages in forums, online discussions and threads, files and pictures). Not providing these optional data will not put the participants in a disadvantaged position.

### (b) Information relative to staff of National Agencies and Erasmus+ sending institutions/organisations are provided by these institutions and DG EAC to EACEA:

**Institutional data** : Project number, PIC number, project name, project start date, project end date, project contact person, project contact telephone number, project contact e-mail, number of licences for language assessments and number of licences for language courses.

### (c) Purpose of the processing:

The OLS purpose is to provide a scheme for measuring progress in language competences through mobility. The other objective relates to the support of language learning prior to and during the mobility period, to the level which is useful for participant's purpose.

More specifically, the data processing is necessary to:

  * enable OLS to function;
  * allow OLS registrants to communicate and collaborate in the spirit of mutual trust and respect; and,
  * extract aggregate data for statistical purposes.

## 2\. Who has access to your information and to whom is it disclosed?

Personal data will never be used for marketing purposes.

For the purposes detailed above, access to data is strictly limited to:

  * Other registered OLS users may have access to optional data that you submit, e.g., messages in forums, online discussions and threads, files and pictures.
  * European Commission, EACEA and National Agencies: aggregate data only.
  * Service provider Altissia who acts on behalf and under the instructions of EACEA: full set of data.
  * Data related to individual mobility participants is accessible to their sending institution/organisation having an access to the backend licence management system OLS which can then decide on its use.
  * For EVS volunteers, the results will not be communicated to the other organisation(s) in the project.

Whenever possible, data will be processed in an anonymous way, especially if transferred to third parties for research purposes.

## 3\. How do we protect and safeguard your information?

The collected personal data and all related information are stored on secured servers of the service provider (Altissia) for the duration of the contract with the Consortium UCL – ALTISSIA – CLL .

The operations of the service provider's computer centres contractually abide to the European Commission's security directives and provisions established by the Directorate of Security for these kinds of servers and services. The standard security measures exist for the site hosting the Altissia servers, i.e. most recently patched and updated operating system and software, antivirus protection, firewall, regular security auditing and network security scans, applied IT security policy, vulnerability testing and intrusion detection system.

## 4\. How can you verify and rectify your information?

To exercise your rights, such as the right of access and rectification of inaccurate or incomplete personal data, you may do this yourself online. You may also contact the Controller (see below under 6.).

## 5\. How long do we keep your personal data?

Data related to the profile of the user are kept for one year after the user's last login. After one year from the last login, the user profile will automatically be set to inactive, i.e., no longer visible to other users. A notification is sent to the user to inform her/him that her/his profile has been set to inactive and that he/she can re-activate his/her account by logging in again. A second and final reminder is sent after two additional years informing the user that 3 years after her/his last login, his/her profile will be deactivated permanently. All personal information is then made anonymous.

Data related to statistics and research purposes is kept for the entire duration of the OLS. At the end of the contract, the Consortium UCL – ALTISSIA – CLL will hand over all information and data to the EACEA and not keep a copy of confidential information, documents and personal data in whatever format. The data remain solely for research and monitoring purposes at the disposal of the EACEA, the European Commission, NAs and Erasmus+ sending institutions/organisations, Altissia on behalf of the Consortium UCL – ALTISSIA – CLL and other third parties under the authorisation of the Data Controller in an aggregated format.

## 6\. Contact information

The data processing operations are under the responsibility of the Data Controller:

Head of Unit A1 - Erasmus+: Schools, Prospective Initiatives, Programme Coordination

Education, Audiovisual and Culture Executive Agency

Office: BOU2 01/017

Avenue du Bourget 1

1049 Brussels

Belgium

For any questions on your rights and the exercise of your rights related to the processing of personal data (like access and rectification of your personal data), please feel free to contact the Controller of the OLS at this address: [EACEA-EPLUS-OLS@ec.europa.eu](mailto:EACEA-EPLUS-OLS@ec.europa.eu)

## **  
** 7\. Recourse

In case of conflict on any Personal Data Protection issue you can address yourself to the Controller at the above mentioned address and functional mailbox. You can also contact EACEA's Data Protection Officer at the following email address: [eacea-data-protection@ec.europa.eu](mailto:eacea-data-protection@ec.europa.eu).

Should the conflict not be resolved by the Controller or the Data Protection Officer you may lodge a complaint with the European Data Protection Supervisor at any time:

Website - [http://www.edps.europa.eu](http://www.edps.europa.eu/);

Email - [edps@edps.europa.eu](mailto:edps@edps.europa.eu).

## 8\. Legal basis

The main legal basis of the processing of personal data is:

  * COMMISSION IMPLEMENTING DECISION of 18 December 2013 establishing the ‘Education, Audiovisual and Culture Executive Agency’ and repealing Decision 2009/336/EC (2013/776/EU): Article 3 (a).
  * 'Erasmus+': the Union programme for education, training, youth and sport established by Regulation (EU) No 1288/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 December 2013 and repealing Decisions No 1719/2006/EC, No 1720/2006/EC and No 1298/2008/EC (OJ L 347 of 20.12.2013, p. 50–73): 
    * Article 5 (e) foresees that "[the Programme shall pursue the following specific objectives] to improve the teaching and learning of languages and to promote the Union's broad linguistic diversity and intercultural awareness." In addition, Annex I foresees "The Programme will be monitored closely on the basis of a set of indicators intended to measure the extent to which the general and specific objectives of the Programme have been achieved and with a view to minimising administrative burdens and costs. To that end, data will be collected as regards the following set of key indicators". The indicator under "Education and training" specifies "The percentage of participants in long-term mobility declaring that they have increased their language skills".

[1] _OJ L8 of 12.1.2001, p. 1._
